<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
  xml:id="admin-caasp-cephconfig">
<!-- ============================================================== -->
 <title>Configuration</title>
 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:editurl>https://github.com/SUSE/doc-ses/edit/master/xml/</dm:editurl>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
   <dm:release>SES 7</dm:release>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>
 <sect1 xml:id="configuration">
  <title>&ceph; configuration</title>

  <para>
   For almost any &ceph; cluster, the user will want&mdash;and may need&mdash;
   to change some &ceph; configurations. These changes often may be
   warranted in order to alter performance to meet SLAs, or to update default
   data resiliency settings.
  </para>

  <warning>
   <para>
    Modify &ceph; settings carefully, and review the &ceph; configuration
    documentation before making any changes. Changing the settings could result
    in unhealthy daemons or even data loss if used incorrectly.
   </para>
  </warning>

  <sect2 xml:id="required-configurations">
   <title>Required configurations</title>
   <para>
    &rook; and &ceph; both strive to make configuration as easy as possible,
    but there are some configuration options which users are well advised to
    consider for any production cluster.
   </para>
   <sect3 xml:id="default-pg-and-pgp-counts">
    <title>Default PG and PGP counts</title>
    <para>
     The number of PGs and PGPs can be configured on a per-pool basis, but it
     is highly advised to set default values that are appropriate for your
     &ceph; cluster. Appropriate values depend on the number of OSDs the user
     expects to have backing each pool.
    </para>
    <para>
     Pools created prior to v1.1 will have a default PG count of 100. Pools
     created after v1.1 will have &ceph;'s default PG count.
    </para>
    <para>
     An easier option exists for &rookceph; clusters running &ceph; Nautilus
     (v14.2.x) or newer. Nautilus introduced the PG auto-scaler mgr module
     capable of automatically managing PG and PGP values for pools.
    </para>
    <para>
     In Nautilus, this module is not enabled by default, but can be enabled by
     the following setting in the CephCluster CR:
    </para>
<screen>
  spec:
    mgr:
      modules:
      - name: pg_autoscaler
        enabled: true
</screen>
    <para>
     In Octopus (v15.2.x), this module is enabled by default without the
     aforementioned setting.
    </para>
    <para>
     With that setting, the autoscaler will be enabled for all new pools. If
     you do not desire to have the autoscaler enabled for all new pools, you
     will need to use the &rook; toolbox to enable the module and enable the
     autoscaling on individual pools.
    </para>
    <para>
     The autoscaler is not enabled for the existing pools after enabling the
     module. So if you want to enable the autoscaling for these existing pools,
     they must be configured from the toolbox.
    </para>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="specifying-configuration-options">
   <title>Specifying configuration options</title>
   <sect3 xml:id="toolbox-ceph-cli">
    <title>Toolbox and the &ceph; CLI</title>
    <para>
     The most recommended way of configuring &ceph; is to set &ceph;'s
     configuration directly. The first method for doing so is to use &ceph;'s
     CLI from the &rookceph; toolbox pod. From the toolbox, the user can change
     &ceph; configurations, enable manager modules, create users and pools, and
     much more.
    </para>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 xml:id="rook-ceph-dashboard">
    <title>&dashboard;</title>
    <para>
     The &dashboard; is another way of setting some of &ceph;’s configuration
     directly. Configuration by the &dashboard; is recommended with the same
     priority as configuration via the &ceph; CLI (above).
    </para>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 xml:id="advanced-configuration-via-ceph-conf-override-configmap">
    <title>Advanced configuration via <filename>ceph.conf</filename> overrides ConfigMap</title>
    <para>
     Setting configuration options via &ceph;’s CLI requires that at least
     one MON be available for the configuration options to be set, and setting
     configuration options via dashboard requires at least one mgr to be
     available. &ceph; may also have a small number of very advanced settings
     that are not able to be modified easily via CLI or dashboard. The
     <emphasis role="strong">least</emphasis> recommended method for
     configuring &ceph; is intended as a last-resort fallback in situations
     like these.
    </para>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
