<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="storage.bp.srv_maint">
 <title>Server Maintenance</title>
 <para/>
 <sect1 xml:id="storage.bp.srv_maint.add_server">
  <title>Adding a Server to a Cluster</title>

  <tip>
   <para>
    When adding an OSD to an existing cluster, be aware that the cluster will
    be rebalancing for some time afterwards. To minimize the rebalancing
    periods, it is best to add all the OSDs you intend to add at the same time.
   </para>
  </tip>

  <para>
   If you are adding an OSD to a cluster, follow
   <xref linkend="storage.bp.inst.add_osd_cephdeploy"/>.
  </para>

  <para>
   If you are adding a monitor to a cluster, follow
   <xref linkend="storage.bp.inst.add_rm_monitor"/>.
  </para>

  <important>
   <para>
    After adding a monitor, make sure that
    <filename>/etc/ceph/ceph.conf</filename> files on each server point to the
    new monitor as well so that it works after the next reboot.
   </para>
  </important>

  <tip>
   <para>
    Adding an OSD and monitor on the same server is recommended only for small
    size clusters. Although the monitor can share disk with the operating
    system (preferably an SSD disk for performance reasons), it should
    <emphasis>never</emphasis> share disk with an OSD.
   </para>
  </tip>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="storage.bp.srv_maint.rm_server">
  <title>Removing a Server from a Cluster</title>

  <para>
   When removing an OSD from an existing cluster, make sure there are enough
   OSDs left in the cluster so that the replication rules can be followed. Also
   be aware that the cluster will be rebalancing for some time after removing
   the OSD.
  </para>

  <para>
   If you are removing an OSD from a cluster, follow
   <xref linkend="storage.bp.disk.del"/>.
  </para>

  <para>
   If you are removing a monitor from a cluster, follow
   <xref linkend="storage.bp.inst.add_rm_monitor.rmmon"/>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="storage.bp.srv_maint.fds_inc">
  <title>Increasing File Descriptors</title>

  <para>
   For OSD daemons, the read/write operations are critical to keep the &ceph;
   cluster balanced. They often need to have many files open for reading and
   writing at the same time. On the OS level, the maximum number of
   simultaneously open files is called 'maximum number of file descriptors'.
  </para>

  <para>
   To prevent OSDs from running out of file descriptors, you can override the
   OS default value and specify the number in
   <filename>/etc/ceph/ceph.conf</filename>, for example:
  </para>

<screen>max_open_files = 131072</screen>

  <para>
   After you change <option>max_open_files</option>, you need to restart the
   OSD service on the relevant &ceph; node.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
