<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="storage.bp.performance">
 <title>Performance Diagnosis</title>
 <para/>
 <sect1 xml:id="storage.bp.performance.slowosd">
  <title>Finding Slow OSDs</title>

  <para>
   When tuning the cluster performance, it is very important to identify slow
   storage/OSDs within the cluster. The reason is that if the data is written
   to the slow(est) disk, the complete write operation slows down as it always
   waits until it is finished on all the related disks.
  </para>

  <para>
   It is not trivial to locate the storage bottleneck. You need to examine each
   and every OSD to find out the ones slowing down the write process. To do a
   benchmark on a single OSD, run:
  </para>

<screen role="ceph_tell_osd_bench"><command>ceph tell</command> <replaceable>osd_id</replaceable> bench</screen>

  <para>
   For example:
  </para>

<screen>&prompt.cephuser;ceph tell osd.0 bench
 { "bytes_written": 1073741824,
   "blocksize": 4194304,
   "bytes_per_sec": "19377779.000000"}</screen>

  <para>
   Then you need to run this command on each OSD and compare the
   <literal>bytes_per_sec</literal> value to get the slow(est) OSDs.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="storage.bp.performance.net_issues">
  <title>Is My Network Causing Issues?</title>

  <para>
   There are more reasons why the cluster performance may become weak. One of
   them can be network problems. In such case, you may notice the cluster
   reaching quorum, OSD and monitor nodes going offline, data transfers taking
   a long time, or a lot of reconnect attempts.
  </para>

  <para>
   To check whether cluster performance is degraded by network problems,
   inspect the &ceph; log files under the <filename>/var/log/ceph</filename>
   directory.
  </para>

  <para>
   To fix network issues on the cluster, focus on the following points:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Basic network diagnostics. Try to ping between cluster nodes and pay
     attention to data loss and response times.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Network performance benchmark. Use tools such as Netperf to measure the
     performance of your network.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Check firewall settings on cluster nodes. Make sure they do not block
     ports/protocols required by &ceph; operation. See
     <xref linkend="storage.bp.net.firewall"/> for more information on firewall
     settings.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Check the networking hardware, such as network cards, cables, or switches,
     for proper operation.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <tip>
   <title>Separate Network</title>
   <para>
    To ensure fast and safe network communication between cluster nodes, set up
    a separate network used exclusively by the cluster OSD and monitor nodes.
   </para>
  </tip>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
