<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE appendix
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<appendix xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
 <title>&ceph; Maintenance Updates Based on Upstream '&cephname;' Point Releases</title>
 <info>
 <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
  <dm:editurl>https://github.com/SUSE/doc-ses/edit/master/xml/</dm:editurl>
  <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  <dm:release>SES 7</dm:release>
 </dm:docmanager>
</info>
 <para>
  Several key packages in &productname; &productnumber; are based on the
  &cephname; release series of &ceph;. When the &ceph; project
  (<link xlink:href="https://github.com/ceph/ceph"/>) publishes new point
  releases in the &cephname; series, &productname; &productnumber; is updated
  to ensure that the product benefits from the latest upstream bugfixes and
  feature backports.
 </para>
 <para>
  This chapter contains summaries of notable changes contained in each upstream
  point release that has been&mdash;or is planned to be&mdash;included in the
  product.
 </para>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect1">&cephname; 15.2.5 Point Release</bridgehead>
 <para>
   The &cephname; point release 15.2.5 brought the following fixes and other changes:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
     &cephfs;: Automatic static subtree partitioning policies may now be
     configured using the new distributed and random ephemeral pinning
     extended attributes on directories. See the following documentation
     for more information: <link xlink:href="https://docs.ceph.com/docs/master/cephfs/multimds/"/>
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
     Monitors now have a config option <option>mon_osd_warn_num_repaired</option>, which is
     set to 10 by default. If any OSD has repaired more than this many I/O
     errors in stored data a <literal>OSD_TOO_MANY_REPAIRS</literal> health warning is generated.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
     Now, when <literal>no scrub</literal> and/or <literal>no deep-scrub</literal>
     flags are set globally or per pool, scheduled scrubs of the type disabled
     will be aborted. All user initiated scrubs are NOT interrupted.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
     Fixed an issue with osdmaps not being trimmed in a healthy cluster.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect1">&cephname; 15.2.4 Point Release</bridgehead>
 <para>
   The &cephname; point release 15.2.4 brought the following fixes and other changes:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
     CVE-2020-10753: rgw: sanitize newlines in s3 CORSConfiguration’s ExposeHeader
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
     &ogw;: The <command>radosgw-admin</command> sub-commands dealing with orphans&mdash;<command>radosgw-admin orphans find</command>,
     <command>radosgw-admin orphans finish</command>, and <command>radosgw-admin orphans list-jobs</command>&mdash;have been deprecated. They had not been actively maintained, and since
     they store intermediate results on the cluster, they could potentially
     fill a nearly-full cluster. They have been replaced by a tool,
     <command>rgw-orphan-list</command>, which is currently considered experimental.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
     RBD: The name of the RBD pool object that is used to store RBD trash purge
     schedule is changed from <literal>rbd_trash_trash_purge_schedule</literal> to
     <literal>rbd_trash_purge_schedule</literal>. Users that have already started using RBD trash
     purge schedule functionality and have per pool or namespace schedules
     configured should copy the <literal>rbd_trash_trash_purge_schedule</literal> object to
     <literal>rbd_trash_purge_schedule</literal> before the upgrade and remove <literal>rbd_trash_purge_schedule</literal>
     using the following commands in every RBD pool and namespace where a trash
     purge schedule was previously configured:
   </para>
<screen>
rados -p <replaceable>pool-name</replaceable> [-N namespace] cp rbd_trash_trash_purge_schedule rbd_trash_purge_schedule
rados -p <replaceable>pool-name</replaceable> [-N namespace] rm rbd_trash_trash_purge_schedule
</screen>
   <para>
     Alternatively, use any other convenient way to restore the schedule after the upgrade.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect1">&cephname; 15.2.3 Point Release</bridgehead>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
     The &cephname; point release 15.2.3 was a hotfix release to address an issue
     where WAL corruption was seen when <option>bluefs_preextend_wal_files</option> and
     <option>bluefs_buffered_io</option> were enabled at the same time. The fix in 15.2.3
     is only a temporary measure (changing the default value of
     <option>bluefs_preextend_wal_files</option> to <literal>false</literal>).
     The permanent fix will be to remove the <option>bluefs_preextend_wal_files</option>
     option completely: this fix will most likely arrive in the 15.2.6 point release.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect1">&cephname; 15.2.2 Point Release</bridgehead>
 <para>
   The &cephname; point release 15.2.2 patched one security vulnerability:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
     CVE-2020-10736: Fixed an authorization bypass in MONs and MGRs
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect1">&cephname; 15.2.1 Point Release</bridgehead>
 <para>
   The &cephname; point release 15.2.1 fixed an issue where upgrading quickly
   from Luminous (SES5.5) to Nautilus (SES6) to &cephname; (SES7) caused OSDs
   to crash. In addition, it patched two security vulnerabilities that were
   present in the initial &cephname; (15.2.0) release:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
     CVE-2020-1759: Fixed nonce reuse in msgr V2 secure mode
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
     CVE-2020-1760: Fixed XSS due to RGW GetObject header-splitting
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
</appendix>
