<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- Converted by suse-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha-ceph-as-iscsi">
<!-- ============================================================== -->
 <title>Installation of iSCSI Gateway</title>
 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:editurl>https://github.com/SUSE/doc-ses/edit/maintenance/ses6/xml/</dm:editurl>
   <dm:maintainer>tbazant@suse.com</dm:maintainer>
   <dm:status>editing</dm:status>
   <dm:deadline/>
   <dm:priority/>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
   <dm:languages/>
   <dm:release>SES 6</dm:release>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>
 <para>
  iSCSI is a storage area network (SAN) protocol that allows clients (called
  <emphasis>initiators</emphasis>) to send SCSI commands to SCSI storage
  devices (<emphasis>targets</emphasis>) on remote servers. &productname;
  &productnumber; includes a facility that opens &ceph; storage management to
  heterogeneous clients, such as &mswin;* and &vmware;* vSphere, through the
  iSCSI protocol. Multipath iSCSI access enables availability and scalability
  for these clients, and the standardized iSCSI protocol also provides an
  additional layer of security isolation between clients and the &productname;
  &productnumber; cluster. The configuration facility is named &ceiscsi;. Using
  &ceiscsi;, &ceph; storage administrators can define thin-provisioned,
  replicated, highly-available volumes supporting read-only snapshots,
  read-write clones, and automatic resizing with &ceph; RADOS Block Device
  (RBD). Administrators can then export volumes either via a single &ceiscsi;
  gateway host, or via multiple gateway hosts supporting multipath failover.
  Linux, &mswin;, and &vmware; hosts can connect to volumes using the iSCSI
  protocol, which makes them available like any other SCSI block device. This
  means &productname; &productnumber; customers can effectively run a complete
  block-storage infrastructure subsystem on &ceph; that provides all the
  features and benefits of a conventional SAN, enabling future growth.
 </para>
 <para>
  This chapter introduces detailed information to set up a &ceph; cluster
  infrastructure together with an iSCSI gateway so that the client hosts can
  use remotely stored data as local storage devices using the iSCSI protocol.
 </para>
 <sect1 xml:id="ceph-iscsi-iscsi">
  <title>iSCSI Block Storage</title>

  <para>
   iSCSI is an implementation of the Small Computer System Interface (SCSI)
   command set using the Internet Protocol (IP), specified in RFC 3720. iSCSI
   is implemented as a service where a client (the initiator) talks to a server
   (the target) via a session on TCP port 3260. An iSCSI target's IP address
   and port are called an iSCSI portal, where a target can be exposed through
   one or more portals. The combination of a target and one or more portals is
   called the target portal group (TPG).
  </para>

  <para>
   The underlying data link layer protocol for iSCSI is commonly Ethernet. More
   specifically, modern iSCSI infrastructures use 10 Gigabit Ethernet or faster
   networks for optimal throughput. 10 Gigabit Ethernet connectivity between
   the iSCSI gateway and the back-end &ceph; cluster is strongly recommended.
  </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="ceph-iscsi-iscsi-target">
   <title>The Linux Kernel iSCSI Target</title>
   <para>
    The Linux kernel iSCSI target was originally named LIO for linux-iscsi.org,
    the project's original domain and Web site. For some time, no fewer than
    four competing iSCSI target implementations were available for the Linux
    platform, but LIO ultimately prevailed as the single iSCSI reference
    target. The mainline kernel code for LIO uses the simple, but somewhat
    ambiguous name "target", distinguishing between "target core" and a variety
    of front-end and back-end target modules.
   </para>
   <para>
    The most commonly used front-end module is arguably iSCSI. However, LIO
    also supports Fibre Channel (FC), Fibre Channel over Ethernet (FCoE) and
    several other front-end protocols. At this time, only the iSCSI protocol is
    supported by &productname;.
   </para>
   <para>
    The most frequently used target back-end module is one that is capable of
    simply re-exporting any available block device on the target host. This
    module is named iblock. However, LIO also has an RBD-specific back-end
    module supporting parallelized multipath I/O access to RBD images.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="ceph-iscsi-iscsi-initiators">
   <title>iSCSI Initiators</title>
   <para>
    This section introduces brief information on iSCSI initiators used on
    Linux, &mswin;, and &vmware; platforms.
   </para>
   <sect3>
    <title>Linux</title>
    <para>
     The standard initiator for the Linux platform is
     <systemitem>open-iscsi</systemitem>. <systemitem>open-iscsi</systemitem>
     launches a daemon, <systemitem>iscsid</systemitem>, which the user can
     then use to discover iSCSI targets on any given portal, log in to targets,
     and map iSCSI volumes. <systemitem>iscsid</systemitem> communicates with
     the SCSI mid layer to create in-kernel block devices that the kernel can
     then treat like any other SCSI block device on the system. The
     <systemitem>open-iscsi</systemitem> initiator can be deployed in
     conjunction with the Device Mapper Multipath
     (<systemitem>dm-multipath</systemitem>) facility to provide a highly
     available iSCSI block device.
    </para>
   </sect3>
   <sect3>
    <title>&mswin; and &hyper;</title>
    <para>
     The default iSCSI initiator for the &mswin; operating system is the
     Microsoft iSCSI initiator. The iSCSI service can be configured via a
     graphical user interface (GUI), and supports multipath I/O for high
     availability.
    </para>
   </sect3>
   <sect3>
    <title>&vmware;</title>
    <para>
     The default iSCSI initiator for &vmware; vSphere and ESX is the &vmware;
     ESX software iSCSI initiator, <systemitem>vmkiscsi</systemitem>. When
     enabled, it can be configured either from the vSphere client, or using the
     <command>vmkiscsi-tool</command> command. You can then format storage
     volumes connected through the vSphere iSCSI storage adapter with VMFS, and
     use them like any other VM storage device. The &vmware; initiator also
     supports multipath I/O for high availability.
    </para>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="ceph-iscsi-lrbd">
  <title>General Information about &ceiscsi;</title>

  <para>
   &ceiscsi; combines the benefits of RADOS Block Devices with the ubiquitous
   versatility of iSCSI. By employing &ceiscsi; on an iSCSI target host (known
   as the &igw;), any application that needs to make use of block storage can
   benefit from &ceph;, even if it does not speak any &ceph; client protocol.
   Instead, users can use iSCSI or any other target front-end protocol to
   connect to an LIO target, which translates all target I/O to RBD storage
   operations.
  </para>

  <figure>
   <title>&ceph; Cluster with a Single iSCSI Gateway</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="lrbd_scheme1.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="lrbd_scheme1.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   &ceiscsi; is inherently highly-available and supports multipath operations.
   Thus, downstream initiator hosts can use multiple iSCSI gateways for both
   high availability and scalability. When communicating with an iSCSI
   configuration with more than one gateway, initiators may load-balance iSCSI
   requests across multiple gateways. In the event of a gateway failing, being
   temporarily unreachable, or being disabled for maintenance, I/O will
   transparently continue via another gateway.
  </para>

  <figure>
   <title>&ceph; Cluster with Multiple iSCSI Gateways</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="lrbd_scheme2.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="lrbd_scheme2.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="ceph-iscsi-deploy">
  <title>Deployment Considerations</title>

  <para>
   A minimum configuration of &productname; &productnumber; with &ceiscsi;
   consists of the following components:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     A &ceph; storage cluster. The &ceph; cluster consists of a minimum of four
     physical servers hosting at least eight object storage daemons (OSDs)
     each. In such a configuration, three OSD nodes also double as a monitor
     (MON) host.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     An iSCSI target server running the LIO iSCSI target, configured via
     &ceiscsi;.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     An iSCSI initiator host, running <systemitem>open-iscsi</systemitem>
     (Linux), the Microsoft iSCSI Initiator (&mswin;), or any other compatible
     iSCSI initiator implementation.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
   A recommended production configuration of &productname; &productnumber; with
   &ceiscsi; consists of:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     A &ceph; storage cluster. A production &ceph; cluster consists of any
     number of (typically more than 10) OSD nodes, each typically running 10-12
     object storage daemons (OSDs), with no fewer than three dedicated MON
     hosts.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Several iSCSI target servers running the LIO iSCSI target, configured via
     &ceiscsi;. For iSCSI fail-over and load-balancing, these servers must run
     a kernel supporting the <systemitem>target_core_rbd</systemitem> module.
     Update packages are available from the &sls; maintenance channel.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Any number of iSCSI initiator hosts, running
     <systemitem>open-iscsi</systemitem> (Linux), the Microsoft iSCSI Initiator
     (&mswin;), or any other compatible iSCSI initiator implementation.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="ceph-iscsi-install">
  <title>Installation and Configuration</title>

  <para>
   This section describes steps to install and configure an &igw; on top of
   &productname;.
  </para>

  <sect2>
   <title>Deploy the &igw; to a &ceph; Cluster</title>
   <para>
    You can deploy the &igw; either during the &ceph; cluster deployment
    process, or add it to an existing cluster using &deepsea;.
   </para>
   <para>
    To include the &igw; during the cluster deployment process, refer to
    <xref
     linkend="policy-role-assignment"/>.
   </para>
   <para>
    To add the &igw; to an existing cluster, refer to
    <xref linkend="salt-adding-services"/>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
   <title>Create RBD Images</title>
   <para>
    RBD images are created in the &ceph; store and subsequently exported to
    iSCSI. We recommend that you use a dedicated RADOS pool for this purpose.
    You can create a volume from any host that is able to connect to your
    storage cluster using the &ceph; <command>rbd</command> command line
    utility. This requires the client to have at least a minimal ceph.conf
    configuration file, and appropriate CephX authentication credentials.
   </para>
   <para>
    To create a new volume for subsequent export via iSCSI, use the
    <command>rbd create</command> command, specifying the volume size in
    megabytes. For example, in order to create a 100 GB volume named 'testvol'
    in the pool named 'iscsi-images', run:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.cephuser;rbd --pool iscsi-images create --size=102400 'testvol'</screen>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="ceph-iscsi-rbd-export">
   <title>Export RBD Images via iSCSI</title>
   <para>
    To export RBD images via iSCSI, you can use either &dashboard; Web
    interface or the &ceiscsi; &gwcli; utility. In this section we will focus
    on &gwcli; only, demonstrating how to create an iSCSI target that exports
    an RBD image using the command line.
   </para>
   <note>
    <para>
     Only the following RBD image features are supported:
     <option>layering</option>, <option>striping (v2)</option>,
     <option>exclusive-lock</option>, <option>fast-diff</option>, and
     <option>data-pool</option>. RBD images with any other feature enabled
     cannot be exported.
    </para>
   </note>
   <para>
    As &rootuser;, start the iSCSI gateway command line interface:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;&gwcli;</screen>
   <para>
    Go to <literal>iscsi-targets</literal> and create a target with the name
    <literal>iqn.2003-01.org.linux-iscsi.iscsi.<replaceable>SYSTEM-ARCH</replaceable>:testvol</literal>:
   </para>
<screen>
&prompt.gwcli; /> cd /iscsi-targets
&prompt.gwcli; /iscsi-targets> create iqn.2003-01.org.linux-iscsi.iscsi.<replaceable>SYSTEM-ARCH</replaceable>:testvol
</screen>
   <para>
    Create the iSCSI gateways by specifying the gateway <literal>name</literal>
    and <literal>ip</literal> address:
   </para>
<screen>
&prompt.gwcli; /iscsi-targets> cd iqn.2003-01.org.linux-iscsi.iscsi.<replaceable>SYSTEM-ARCH</replaceable>:testvol/gateways
&prompt.gwcli; /iscsi-target...tvol/gateways> create iscsi1 192.168.124.104
&prompt.gwcli; /iscsi-target...tvol/gateways> create iscsi2 192.168.124.105
</screen>
   <tip>
    <para>
     Use the <literal>help</literal> command to show the list of available
     commands in the current configuration node.
    </para>
   </tip>
   <para>
    Add the RBD image with the name 'testvol' in the pool 'iscsi-images':
   </para>
<screen>
&prompt.gwcli; /iscsi-target...tvol/gateways> cd /disks
&prompt.gwcli; /disks> attach iscsi-images/testvol
</screen>
   <para>
    Map the RBD image to the target:
   </para>
<screen>
&prompt.gwcli; /disks> cd /iscsi-targets/iqn.2003-01.org.linux-iscsi.iscsi.<replaceable>SYSTEM-ARCH</replaceable>:testvol/disks
&prompt.gwcli; /iscsi-target...testvol/disks> add iscsi-images/testvol
</screen>
   <note>
    <para>
     You can use lower level tools, such as <command>targetcli</command>, to
     query the local configuration, but not to modify it.
    </para>
   </note>
   <tip>
    <para>
     You can use the <command>ls</command> command to review the configuration.
     Some configuration nodes also support the <command>info</command> command,
     which can be used to display more detailed information.
    </para>
   </tip>
   <para>
    Note that, by default, ACL authentication is enabled so this target is not
    accessible yet. Check <xref linkend="iscsi-lrbd-autentication" /> for more
    information about authentication and access control.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="iscsi-lrbd-autentication">
   <title>Authentication and Access Control</title>
   <para>
    &iscsi; authentication is flexible and covers many authentication
    possibilities.
   </para>
   <sect3>
    <title>No Authentication</title>
    <para>
     'No authentication' means that any initiator will be able to access any
     LUNs on the corresponding target. You can enable 'No authentication' by
     disabling the ACL authentication:
    </para>
<screen>
&prompt.gwcli; /> cd /iscsi-targets/iqn.2003-01.org.linux-iscsi.iscsi.<replaceable>SYSTEM-ARCH</replaceable>:testvol/hosts
&prompt.gwcli; /iscsi-target...testvol/hosts> auth disable_acl
</screen>
   </sect3>
   <sect3>
    <title>ACL Authentication</title>
    <para>
     When using initiator name based ACL authentication, only the defined
     initiators are allowed to connect. You can define an initiator by doing:
    </para>
<screen>
&prompt.gwcli; /> cd /iscsi-targets/iqn.2003-01.org.linux-iscsi.iscsi.<replaceable>SYSTEM-ARCH</replaceable>:testvol/hosts
&prompt.gwcli; /iscsi-target...testvol/hosts> create iqn.1996-04.de.suse:01:e6ca28cc9f20
</screen>
    <para>
     Defined initiators will be able to connect, but will only have access to
     the RBD images that were explicitly added to the initiator:
    </para>
<screen>
&prompt.gwcli; /iscsi-target...:e6ca28cc9f20> disk add rbd/testvol
</screen>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 xml:id="chap-auth-password">
    <title>CHAP Authentication</title>
    <para>
     In addition to the ACL, you can enable the CHAP authentication by
     specifying a user name and password for each initiator:
    </para>
<screen>
&prompt.gwcli; /> cd /iscsi-targets/iqn.2003-01.org.linux-iscsi.iscsi.<replaceable>SYSTEM-ARCH</replaceable>:testvol/hosts/iqn.1996-04.de.suse:01:e6ca28cc9f20
&prompt.gwcli; /iscsi-target...:e6ca28cc9f20> auth username=common12 password=pass12345678
</screen>
    <note>
     <para>
      User names must have a length of 8 to 64 characters and can only contain
      letters, '.', '@', '-', '_' or ':'.
     </para>
     <para>
      Passwords must have a length of 12 to 16 characters and can only contain
      letters, '@', '-', '_' or '/'.
     </para>
    </note>
    <para>
     Optionally, you can also enable the CHAP mutual authentication by
     specifying the <option>mutual_username</option> and
     <option>mutual_password</option> parameters in the <command>auth</command>
     command.
    </para>
   </sect3>
   <sect3>
    <title>Discovery and Mutual Authentication</title>
    <para>
     <emphasis>Discovery authentication</emphasis> is independent of the
     previous authentication methods. It requires credentials for browsing, it
     is optional, and can be configured by:
    </para>
<screen>
&prompt.gwcli; /> cd /iscsi-targets
&prompt.gwcli; /iscsi-targets> discovery_auth username=du123456 password=dp1234567890
</screen>
    <note>
     <para>
      User-names must have a length of 8 to 64 characters and can only contain
      letters, '.', '@', '-', '_' or ':'.
     </para>
     <para>
      Passwords must have a length of 12 to 16 characters and can only contain
      letters, '@', '-', '_' or '/'.
     </para>
    </note>
    <para>
     Optionally, you can also specify the <option>mutual_username</option> and
     <option>mutual_password</option> parameters in the
     <command>discovery_auth</command> command.
    </para>
    <para>
     Discovery authentication can be disabled by using the following command:
    </para>
<screen>
&prompt.gwcli; /iscsi-targets> discovery_auth nochap
</screen>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="ceph-iscsi-rbd-advanced">
   <title>Advanced Settings</title>
   <para>
    &ceiscsi; can be configured with advanced parameters which are subsequently
    passed on to the LIO I/O target. The parameters are divided up into
    'target' and 'disk' parameters.
   </para>
   <warning>
    <para>
     Unless otherwise noted, changing these parameters from the default setting
     is not recommended.
    </para>
   </warning>
   <sect3>
    <title>Target Settings</title>
    <para>
     You can view the value of these settings by using the
     <command>info</command> command:
    </para>
<screen>
&prompt.gwcli; /> cd /iscsi-targets/iqn.2003-01.org.linux-iscsi.iscsi.<replaceable>SYSTEM-ARCH</replaceable>:testvol
&prompt.gwcli; /iscsi-target...i.<replaceable>SYSTEM-ARCH</replaceable>:testvol> info
</screen>
    <para>
     And change a setting using the <command>reconfigure</command> command:
    </para>
<screen>
&prompt.gwcli; /iscsi-target...i.<replaceable>SYSTEM-ARCH</replaceable>:testvol> reconfigure login_timeout 20
</screen>
    <para>
     The available 'target' settings are:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>default_cmdsn_depth</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Default CmdSN (Command Sequence Number) depth. Limits the amount of
        requests that an iSCSI initiator can have outstanding at any moment.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>default_erl</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Default error recovery level.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>login_timeout</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Login timeout value in seconds.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>netif_timeout</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        NIC failure timeout in seconds.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>prod_mode_write_protect</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        If set to 1, prevents writes to LUNs.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
   </sect3>
   <sect3>
    <title>Disk Settings</title>
    <para>
     You can view the value of these settings by using the
     <command>info</command> command:
    </para>
<screen>
&prompt.gwcli; /> cd /disks/rbd/testvol
&prompt.gwcli; /disks/rbd/testvol> info
</screen>
    <para>
     And change a setting using the <command>reconfigure</command> command:
    </para>
<screen>
&prompt.gwcli; /disks/rbd/testvol> reconfigure rbd/testvol emulate_pr 0
</screen>
    <para>
     The available 'disk' settings are:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>block_size</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Block size of the underlying device.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>emulate_3pc</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        If set to 1, enables Third Party Copy.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>emulate_caw</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        If set to 1, enables Compare and Write.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>emulate_dpo</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        If set to 1, turns on Disable Page Out.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>emulate_fua_read</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        If set to 1, enables Force Unit Access read.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>emulate_fua_write</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        If set to 1, enables Force Unit Access write.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>emulate_model_alias</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        If set to 1, uses the back-end device name for the model alias.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>emulate_pr</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        If set to 0, support for SCSI Reservations, including Persistent Group
        Reservations, is disabled. While disabled, the SES iSCSI Gateway can
        ignore reservation state, resulting in improved request latency.
       </para>
       <tip>
        <para>
         Setting backstore_emulate_pr to 0 is recommended if iSCSI initiators
         do not require SCSI Reservation support.
        </para>
       </tip>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>emulate_rest_reord</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        If set to 0, the Queue Algorithm Modifier has Restricted Reordering.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>emulate_tas</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        If set to 1, enables Task Aborted Status.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>emulate_tpu</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        If set to 1, enables Thin Provisioning Unmap.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>emulate_tpws</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        If set to 1, enables Thin Provisioning Write Same.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>emulate_ua_intlck_ctrl</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        If set to 1, enables Unit Attention Interlock.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>emulate_write_cache</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        If set to 1, turns on Write Cache Enable.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>enforce_pr_isids</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        If set to 1, enforces persistent reservation ISIDs.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>is_nonrot</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        If set to 1, the backstore is a non-rotational device.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>max_unmap_block_desc_count</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Maximum number of block descriptors for UNMAP.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>max_unmap_lba_count:</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Maximum number of LBAs for UNMAP.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>max_write_same_len</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Maximum length for WRITE_SAME.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>optimal_sectors</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Optimal request size in sectors.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>pi_prot_type</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        DIF protection type.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>queue_depth</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Queue depth.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>unmap_granularity</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        UNMAP granularity.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>unmap_granularity_alignment</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        UNMAP granularity alignment.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>force_pr_aptpl</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        When enabled, LIO will always write out the <emphasis>persistent
        reservation</emphasis> state to persistent storage, regardless of
        whether or not the client has requested it via
        <option>aptpl=1</option>. This has no effect with the kernel RBD
        back-end for LIO&mdash;it always persists PR state. Ideally, the
        <option>target_core_rbd</option> option should force it to '1' and
        throw an error if someone tries to disable it via configfs.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>unmap_zeroes_data</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Affects whether LIO will advertise LBPRZ to SCSI initiators, indicating
        that zeros will be read back from a region following UNMAP or WRITE
        SAME with an unmap bit.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="iscsi-tcmu">
  <title>Exporting &rbd; Images Using <systemitem>tcmu-runner</systemitem></title>

  <para>
   The &ceiscsi; supports both <option>rbd</option> (kernel-based) and
   <option>user:rbd</option> (tcmu-runner) backstores, making all the management
   transparent and independent of the backstore.
  </para>

  <warning>
   <title>Technology Preview</title>
   <para>
    <systemitem>tcmu-runner</systemitem> based &igw; deployments are currently
    a technology preview.
   </para>
  </warning>

  <para>
   Unlike kernel-based &igw; deployments, <systemitem>tcmu-runner</systemitem>
   based &igw;s do not offer support for multipath I/O or SCSI Persistent
   Reservations.
  </para>

  <para>
   To export an &rbd; image using <systemitem>tcmu-runner</systemitem>, all you
   need to do is specify the <option>user:rbd</option> backstore when attaching
   the disk:
  </para>

<screen>
&prompt.gwcli; /disks> attach rbd/testvol backstore=user:rbd
</screen>

  <note>
   <para>
    When using <systemitem>tcmu-runner</systemitem>, the exported RBD image
    must have the <option>exclusive-lock</option> feature enabled.
   </para>
  </note>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
