<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="ceph-hardening-meassures-network">
 <title>Network</title>

  <para>
&productname; is a complex system that communicates internally and externally via networks. As with all other systems careful design and control of this 
network access is vital for ensuring the security of your cluster.
  </para>

  <para>
While &productname; can be run with a single network connected to all nodes it is important for security to use the setup 
recommended in <xref linkend="network-overview"/> and have two separate networks connected to your cluster. 
It is to be preferred to have physically separate networks. If this isn't possible you can use VLANs to logically separate them.
  </para>

  <para>
The
internal network is used for replication and recovery and should not be available to clients. Unless special measures are taken (described in  
<xref linkend="ceph-hardening-meassures-confidentiality"/>) data stored on &productname; is transfered in cleartext on this network. Even when you ensure that
data is transfered only in encrypted form it is highly recommended to use a dedicated network.
  </para>

  <para>
The public network is used as interface for clients
and can be restricted to the minimal necessary access and also be monitored for anomalies.
  </para>

  <para>
These are the TCP ports that are necessary for various services:

   <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
  3300, 6789: Monitor nodes
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
  6800-7300: OSD nodes
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
  6800-7300: MGR nodes
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
  6800: MDS nodes
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
  80,443,7480: Radosgw
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
  8080,8443: Dashboard
    </para>
  </listitem> 
   <listitem>
    <para>
    4505,4506: Administration via salt
    </para>
  </listitem> 
  </itemizedlist>
  </para>

  <para>
    You should ensure on a network and on a host level that these ports are only accessible to the strictest possible set of clients. All other ports should be blocked by a default-deny rule. Remember to block the ports you want to deny
    access to for IPv4 and IPv6 if that is enabled in your environment.
  </para>

  <para>
    Consider your use case and then analyze what network access is necessary on each network. E.g. the dashboard usually doesn't need to be accessible to 
    users and access to it can be restricted via firewalls.
    The Ceph Block Device (rbd), Ceph Filesystem (cephfs) and Ceph Object Gateway (rgw) must be available to the clients that use them. If you don't use e.g. rgw or only a limited
    set of users use it you can 
    prevent access to these ports  in general or for groups that don't need access. This limits the damage that can be done if a vulnerability in this component is found.
  </para>

</chapter>

