<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="ceph-hardening-measures-general">
 <title>General</title>
 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:editurl>https://github.com/SUSE/doc-ses/edit/master/xml/</dm:editurl>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
   <dm:release>SES 7</dm:release>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>
 <para>
  Hardening your &productname; installation involves reducing the attack
  surface presented to potential attackers. But this is only the tip of the
  iceberg. All the basic tasks of securing a system applied to &productname; as
  well.
 </para>
 <sect1 xml:id="basic-security-hygiene">
  <title>Basic security hygiene</title>

  <para>
   As with any other system it is important that you practice proper security
   hygiene for you &productname; installation. This includes monitoring a
   suitable channel for security notices
   (<link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/security/cve/"/>) and incorporate
   this in your security tracking.
  </para>

  <para>
   It is mandatory that you install updates in a timely manner. If available,
   you can use threat intelligence to guide you in your update strategy, but
   the sooner you install updates the better. Most organizations do not get
   hacked via 0-day exploits but through long known security issues. If you
   keep your cluster current you improve the security posture dramatically.
  </para>

  <para>
   Installing updates in a &productname; context means that you keep the base
   operating system and the &productname; images up to date. For the base
   operating system you can either use basic command line tools like
   <command>zypper</command> or use &susemgr; to conveniently manage a large
   fleet of machines. Refer to <xref linkend="deploy-cephadm-day2-cephupdate"/>
   on how to keep the &productname; images up to date.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="general-system-hardening">
  <title>General system hardening</title>

  <para>
   Ensuring that the base system is hardened is helping to provide a proper
   base for further hardening measures more specific to &productname;. SUSE
   published a hardening guide for &sls; at
   <link xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/de-de/sles/15-SP1/html/SLES-all/book-hardening.html"/>.
   As &productname; is based on &sls; this contains tips that you can
   incorporate in your security strategy. For example, we recommend that you
   ensure that the systems that host &productname; are physically secure and
   that the boot process is protected is important to have a solid base for
   futher hardenings.
  </para>

  <para>
   We also recommend that you do not add any other workloads on the machines
   that you use for you &productname; cluster. Not only can this negatively
   impact the performance of your &productname; cluster, but you also introduce
   additional risk to your data. If an attacker is able to exploit a
   vulnerability in the unrelated workload, they may be able to use this access
   to compromise your &productname; cluster.
  </para>

  <para>
   If you have a virtualized environment and can easily provision machines, we
   recommend using one machine for each role. Especially the &mon; should be
   stand-alone as they have access to all the key material and running other
   services on them increases their risk profile.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="security-monitoring">
  <title>Monitoring</title>

  <para>
   Without visibility into you systems it is tough to ensure that they run in a
   secure state. You have to either monitor the &productname; cluster itself or
   hook it into your existing monitoring framework to ensure that you are aware
   of changes in the cluster. This mainly helps with availability, but is also
   important for other security goals. For example, you need to notice if
   someone is trying to brute force credentials on the machines by collecting
   and analyzing the logs showing this behavior.
  </para>

  <para>
   You should at least include <filename>/var/log/ceph/cephadm.log</filename>
   into your log analysis setup to make sure you notice changes on your
   &productname; cluster.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
