<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="ceph-hardening2">
 <title>What is covered in this guide</title>

  <para>
    There a three main pillars of security:
   <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
      Confidentiality: Protect information from unauthorized access. 
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
      Integrity: Ensure that information is accurate, consistent and only changed via authorized operations.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
      Availability: The ressource is available when needed.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  </para>

  <para>
    This guide is mainly concerned with confidentiality and integrity. Availability is something you can configure in &productname; easily depending on your requirements.
    It is important, that you consider the availability requirements you have and create the cluster accordingly. E.g. for high availability requirements ensure
    that you don't have single points of failures. Especially Ceph Monitor nodes are critical and need to be available at all times. &productname; makes it easy for you to
    have more nodes for a given service than what you need during normal operations. The more important a service is to you the more redundancy you need to build
    into the system.
  </para>

  <para>
    When you plan for availability make sure you don't plan isolated for the &productname; environment. The requirements also affect other systems that interact with &productname;
    transitively. E.g. if you use LDAP for authentication then a high available &productname; cluster doesn't help you if you LDAP server is not reachable.
  </para>

  <para>
    Confidentiality needs to consider the life cycle of the data in question and the hardware that is used to hold the data. You not only need to take measures
    to ensure the confidentiality of data while it's kept in &productname;, you also need to consider how to safely discard data once you remove hardware. 
  </para>

  <para>
    Integrity requires that the cluster is in a trusted state and that data can only be modified by authorized subjects. Keeping the cluster up to date is the most
    important step in ensuring the integrity of the cluster. Ensuring that only authorized subjects can change data requires that permissions are handed out in a controlled
    and granular way. To ensure that this doesn't deteriorate over time ensure that you regularly review existing permissions and have processes in place that
    revoke them if necessary.
  </para>

  <para>
    This guide will not give you a set of commands you can run and then you're "secure". The new system needs to be integrated into your 
    organizational security framework and the concrete steps often depend on your local configurations. E.g. the recommendations on how to structure the network
    and which ports need to made available then need to be translated into changes of you existing networking hardware, e.g. firewalls.
  </para>

  <para>
    Some suggested changes have performance implications. When you change a plaintext to a encrypted protocol this causes the cluster to have to do more work. 
    This may not be noticeable (e.g. full disk encryption for OSDs, where the CPU is not the limiting factor), but you need to check for your setup if this
    causes issues for you with workloads that are realistic for your environment. 
  </para>
</chapter>
