<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="ceph-hardening1">
 <title>Understanding the Threat</title>
 <info>
 <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
  <dm:editurl>https://github.com/SUSE/doc-ses/edit/master/xml/</dm:editurl>
  <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  <dm:release>SES 7</dm:release>
 </dm:docmanager>
</info>
  <para>
    Before you start to harden your &productname; cluster you need to consider
    the threat landscape you try to control.
  </para>
  <para>
    Depending on your exposure you will need to invest at different levels. You
    need to take differing measures when you use &productname; to provide
    storage on an internal network to a well-known group of employees, as
    opposed to deploying a cluster in a setting where arbitrary internet
    actors can access the cluster. For example, in a public cloud offering as
    storage solution.
  </para>
  <para>
    This is something that needs to happen as a first step as it provides a set
    of guidelines on how much effort you need to invest to get to the level of
    security you need.
  </para>
  <para>
    If you have a mature IT security landscape, you should have already policies
    and standards that you can use to guide you here. You need to have a threat model
    for the planned system and implement measures that you find necessary
    for your situation. Look to you CISO or similar role for guidance on this.
    It is mandatory to understand the potential threats and security requirements
    before you continue.
  </para>

  <para>
    Without a threat model you run the risk of not investing enough or you
    might spent to much on securing a resource than you should. A good approach
    to this is described in the <link xlink:href="https://cheatsheetseries.owasp.org/cheatsheets/Threat_Modeling_Cheat_Sheet.html">OWASP Threat Modeling Cheat Sheet</link>.
  </para>

</chapter>
