<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="tuning-architecture">
 <title>Architecture and Hardware Tuning</title>
 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:editurl>https://github.com/SUSE/doc-ses/edit/master/xml/</dm:editurl>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
   <dm:release>SES 7</dm:release>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>
 <para>
   Architectural tuning includes aspects that range from the low-level design
   of the systems being deployed, up to macro-level decisions about network
   topology and cooling. Not all of these can be covered in this work, but
   guidance will be given where possible.
 </para>
 <para>
   From the top-down view, it is important to think about the physical
   location of nodes, the connectivity available between them, and
   implications of such items as power routing, and fire compartments.
   However, from a performance perspective, it is most important to
   think in terms of the connectivity and what a write actually looks like
   from the cluster perspective.
 </para>
 <para>
   The intention of architectural tuning is to take control of where the
   performance bottlenecks lie. In most cases, it is preferable for the
   bottleneck to lie with the storage device, as that creates a predictable
   pattern of performance degradation and associated limitations. Placing
   the bottleneck in other areas, such as CPU or network, may create
   inconsistent behavior when resources are stressed. This is due to the
   possibility of other processes running, whether recovery, rebalancing,
   garbage collection, and causing inconsistent behavior due to being
   network or CPU bound. When storage is the bottleneck, the degradation
   results in longer response times to queued requests, making this the most
   desireable point at which to place the bottleneck.
 </para>
 <sect1 xml:id="tuning-network">
   <title>Network</title>
   <para>
     The network is the backbone of the cluster, and a failure to implement
     it in a robust manner can cripple the performance of the cluster, no
     matter what other steps are taken. From a best practices perspective,
     this entails implementing a fault-tolerant switching infrastructure that
     can scale the aggregate core bandwidth as the cluster grows. For very
     large clusters, this may entail a leaf and spine architecture, while for
     smaller clusters, it may look like a more familiar hub-and-spoke or
     mesh network.
   </para>
   <para>
     No matter which network architecture is chosen, it is important to
     carefully examine each hop along the path and consider the maximum
     network traffic that could occur during adverse conditions.
   </para>
   <para>
     An example of a bad decision here would be to have a multi-rack cluster
     where each rack contains 16 storage nodes of 24x 7.2k drives where each
     node is connected to a pair of stacked Top-of-Rack (TOR) switches via
     2x25Gb connections. This connectivity is sufficient for 3&nbsp;GB/s per
     connection or 6&nbsp;GB/s total for the node, which is near the maximum that a
     7.2k drive will sustain. The bad decision comes in <emphasis>only</emphasis> using 4x of
     the 25&nbsp;GB interfaces for the uplink. While 100&nbsp;Gb may seem like a
     substantial amount of bandwidth, it translates into only about 10&nbsp;GB/s,
     while the rack is capable of an aggregate of around 48&nbsp;GB/s.
   </para>
   <para>
     During an adverse situation, it is possible that network congestion
     will result in dramatically increased latency, packet delays, drops,
     etc. A simple rememdy would have been to select switches with 4x 100&nbsp;Gb
     uplink ports, resulting in each switch being able to transmit the
     complete, aggregate bandwidth load to the network core.
   </para>
   <para>
     In reality, some level of over-subscription is going to happen in most
     networks, but the smaller the ratio, the better the resulting cluster
     will be able to handle adverse conditions.
   </para>
   <sect2>
     <title>Network Tuning</title>
     <para>
       Here are some general principals to follow when planning
       a &ceph; cluster network:
     </para>
     <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
         <para>
           Utilize 25/50/100&nbsp;GbE connections - The signaling rate is 2.5
           times faster than 10/40&nbsp;GbE resulting in lower latency over
           the wire. The impact from the faster signaling rate would be
           minimal with spinning media and more impactful with faster
           technologies such as NVMe.
         </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
         <para>
           Network bandwidth should be at least the total bandwidth of all
           storage devices present in the storage node
         </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
         <para>
           Usage of VLANs on LACP-bonded Ethernet provides the best
           balance of bandwidth aggregation + fault tolerance
         </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
         <para>
           The network should utilize jumbo-frame Ethernet if all nodes
           connecting to the storage are able to do so, otherwise use the
           standard MTU.
         </para>
       </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
   </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="tuning-node-hw-recommendations">
   <title>Node Hardware Recommendations</title>
   <sect2>
     <title>CPU</title>
     <para>
       There are a lot of options when it comes to processor selection in
       the market today. There are multiple varieties available from the
       major vendors in the &x86; space and a wide array of options in the
       64-bit &arm; space as well. Without regard to the core architecture,
       there is one rule that is always true, and that is that higher
       clockspeed allows more work to be done in the same amount of time.
       This consideration is most important when working with higher speed
       storage and network devices.
     </para>
     <para>
       CPU selection is also an important consideration for specific services.
       Some services, such as metadata servers, NFS, Samba, and ISCSI
       gateways benefit from a smaller number of much faster cores, while
       the OSD nodes need a more core dense solution.
     </para>
     <para>
       A second consideration is whether to use a single socket or multiple
       sockets. The answer to this will depend on the device density,
       type of network hardware being utilized, etc. In many nodes, a single
       socket will provide better performance as the processor interlink is
       a bottleneck, though this would most likely be noticed in an all
       NVMe based node type. The general recommendation is to use a single
       socket whenever possible.
     </para>
     <para>
       When considering which processor to choose, there are several
       considerations aside from clock-speed that should be taken into
       consideration. They include:
     </para>
     <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
         <para>
           <emphasis>Memory bandwidth</emphasis>: &ceph; is a heavy user of RAM, thus the more
           memory bandwidth available, the more performant the node can be.
         </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
         <para>
           <emphasis>Memory layout</emphasis>: Even if the memory selected is fast, if all
           memory channels are not leveraged, performance is being left
           untapped. It is advantageous to ensure that RAM is distributed
           evenly across all channels.
         </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
         <para>
           <emphasis>Offload capabilities</emphasis>: For example, Intel CPUs offer <literal>zlib</literal> and
           Reed-Solomon offloads, the latter being used with erasure
           coding when the ISA plugin is specified.
         </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
         <para>
           <emphasis>PCIe bus speed and lanes</emphasis>: This is particularly important when
           looking at devices with a large number of PCIe devices, like
           NVMe. The bus speed also affects the performance of network
           devices as well.
         </para>
       </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
   </sect2>
   <sect2>
     <title>Storage Device</title>
     <para>
       Storage device selection can dramatically affect the performance and
       reliability of a &ceph; cluster. When building for performance, it
       is important to understand the nature of the device in regard to
       reads/writes and the workloads that will be applied. This is
       particularly true with flash media.
     </para>
     <sect3>
       <title>Device Type</title>
       <para>
         The first recommendation is to ensure that systems utilize
         Enterprise-class storage media. With NVMe and SSD devices,
         this implies a few key items.
       </para>
       <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
           <para>
             More spare cells to deal with media wear-out
           </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
           <para>
             Battery/capacitor to allow completion of buffer dumps
             during unexpected power events
           </para>
         </listitem>
       </itemizedlist>
       <para>
         It is also important to ensure the media being utilized will
         support the workloads of the cluster. For example, if the
         applications using the cluster have a read/write mix of 90/10,
         it is likely acceptable to utilize a read-intensive NVMe device.
         However, if the ratio is flipped or even 50:50, it is a better
         choice to at least consider mixed-use, or write
         intensive media. This selection goes beyond just the media
         durability, but also includes considerations around the design.
         Write-intensive media typically allocate more PCIe lanes to
         handling write requests to the media, ensuring faster commits
         than a read-intensive device would provide under load. Also,
         write intensive devices will most often use faster classes of
         non-volitaile memory technology and/or have large, supercap backed caches.
       </para>
     </sect3>
   </sect2>
   <sect2>
     <title>Device Buses</title>
     <para>
       It is also important to understand the impact of the storage bus and
       hardware pieces along the way. Clearly, 6&nbsp;Gb/s is slower than 12&nbsp;Gb/s,
       and 12&nbsp;Gb/s is slower than PCIe Gen3 (8&nbsp;Gb/s per lane), but what about
       mixing SATA 3&nbsp;Gb/s and SATA 6&nbsp;Gb/s, or mixing 6&nbsp;Gb/s and 12&nbsp;Gb/s SAS?
     </para>
     <para>
       The general rule is not to mix. When a 6&nbsp;Gb/s device is introduced to
       a 12&nbsp;Gb/s bus, the entire bus slows down to 6&nbsp;Gb/s, greatly reducing
       the overall throughput capability. Where this really would hurt is
       in a dense SAS SSD system. If there are 24 SAS SSDs on a two-channel,
       12&nbsp;Gb/s bus and one of the devices is only 6&nbsp;Gb/s, then the 12&nbsp;Gb/s
       SAS drives that can push 850&nbsp;MB/s now oversubscribe the bus due to
       the reduced data rate.
     </para>
     <para>
       Another consideration is the presence of bus expanders. Bus expanders
       allow a system to multi-plex multiple devices on a single channel.
       The result is higher density at lower performance maximum. In some
       cases, the expanders may work acceptably, such as with HDDs, but
       with SSDs, they are likely to quickly become a bottleneck.
     </para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2>
     <title>General Recommendations</title>
     <para>
       Below are some generic tuning options applicable to performance
       tuning for server platforms:
     </para>
     <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
         <para>
           Set firmware Power/Performance controls to the performance profile.
           This should eliminate frequency scaling and ensure that there
           is no added latency caused by it.
         </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
         <para>
           Enable multi-threading on SMT capable CPUs. This extra processing
           power is utilized effectively by &ceph;.
         </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
         <para>
           Ensure all add-in cards are in the optimal slots for performance.
         </para>
       </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
   </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="tuning-cpeh-rocksdb-wal">
   <title>&ceph;</title>
   <sect2>
     <title>RocksDB and WAL</title>
     <para>
       &ceph; makes use of both a Write-Ahead-Log (WAL) and RocksDB. The WAL
       is the internal journal where small writes are queued before commiting
       to the backend storage. RocksDB is where &ceph; stores metadata
       associated with the objects written to bluestore. When using spinning
       media, or perhaps even SSDs, it generally makes sense to locate the
       RocksDB and WAL on a faster device, such as NVMe. When doing so,
       proper sizing of these is critical to ensuring a stable performance
       profile of the cluster over time.
     </para>
     <para>
       From a performance perspective, the rule of thumb is to divide the
       write performance of the WAL/RocksDB device by the write performance
       of the data device. This yields what should be considered to be the
       maximum ratio of data devices per WAL/RocksDB device.
     </para>
     <sect3>
       <title>WAL</title>
       <para>
         The WAL maxes out a bit under two gigabytes. In order to leave
         room for maintenance activities, having about four gigabytes of
         space allocated/allowed is optimal.
       </para>
     </sect3>
     <sect3>
       <title>RocksDB</title>
       <para>
         RocksDB operates with a series of tiered levels, each being an order
         of magnitude larger than the last. Levels one through four are
         256&nbsp;MB, 2.56&nbsp;GB, 25.6&nbsp;GB, 256&nbsp;GB respectively. Allocating appropriate
         space for these is an act of aggregation. Given that few installations
         utilize enough metadata to require the fourth tier, allocating for
         the first three and associated maintenance is sufficient.
         25.6+2.56+.256&nbsp;GB = 28.416&nbsp;GB. Rounding up to 30&nbsp;GB and providing
         100% overhead to allow for maintenance takes the space allocation
         suggested for the first three tiers to 60&nbsp;GB.
       </para>
       <para>
         Making the decision to provision fast space for the fourth tier of
         RocksDB is something completely related to the expected metadata
         load. Protocols like RBD use little metadata, while CephFS is
         somewhere in a mild to moderate amount. S3 and native RADOS can
         utilize the highest amounts of metadata and are generally the
         cases where it starts making sense to evaluate whether the
         fourth tier makes sense to move to faster media.
       </para>
     </sect3>
   </sect2>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
